<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Updates | Alexis Garretson</title>
    <link>https://alexis-catherine.github.io/post/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://alexis-catherine.github.io/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Updates</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© Alexis Garretson 2020</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 26 Jul 2020 16:50:33 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://alexis-catherine.github.io/img/Garretson_headshot_square.jpg</url>
      <title>Updates</title>
      <link>https://alexis-catherine.github.io/post/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Awarded a FUNding Friday Grant from ESIP</title>
      <link>https://alexis-catherine.github.io/post/funding-friday/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Jul 2020 16:50:33 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://alexis-catherine.github.io/post/funding-friday/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Improve provenance tracking, return of results, data credit &amp;amp; attribution, and equity through Columba. Identifies citizen scientists to claim their observations across multiple projects and generates list of research outputs enabled by their work. I&amp;rsquo;m excited to bring this project to life!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Museum Cultural Network Scholar</title>
      <link>https://alexis-catherine.github.io/post/mcn/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Jul 2020 16:50:25 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://alexis-catherine.github.io/post/mcn/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I just found out I was selected as a Museum Computer Network Scholar! I&amp;rsquo;ll be writing about how  citizen science can not only improve visitor experiences and engagement but can also support institutional research and the stewardship of digital resources. Can&amp;rsquo;t wait!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thriving Earth Exchange</title>
      <link>https://alexis-catherine.github.io/post/thriving-earth-exchange/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Jul 2020 16:50:19 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://alexis-catherine.github.io/post/thriving-earth-exchange/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I was invited by the American Geophysical Union&amp;rsquo;s Thriving Earth Exchange program to become a Community Science Fellow in the Science, Policy, and Engagement Cohort funded by the Gordon and Betty Moore Foundation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Community science is becoming an area I&amp;rsquo;m more and more passionate about, and I&amp;rsquo;m excited to continue building my expertise in supporting particularly indigenous and underserved communities in developing scientific infrastructure to support their goals, whether those are related to advocacy, policy, elder knowledge preservation, or other ways of supporting more autonomy and recognition of communities within broader scientific knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>1 Million Women in STEM</title>
      <link>https://alexis-catherine.github.io/post/1-million-women-in-stem/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 May 2020 12:41:50 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://alexis-catherine.github.io/post/1-million-women-in-stem/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;screenshot.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Screenshot&#34;&gt;
I&amp;rsquo;m so excited to add my name to the list of 1 Million Women In STEM. I got to share about how trying things out, including getting involved with Earth Science Information Partners (ESIP), has helped me find my place as a woman in STEM.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My advice to any woman interested in STEM is &amp;ldquo;Try it&amp;rdquo;! There are so many ways to be in a STEM field, and I didn&amp;rsquo;t even know the types of research/science work I get to do every day now were even an option until I had the opportunity to give them a try.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.1mwis.com/profiles/Alexis-Garretson&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Check it out&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>American Alpine Club Researcher</title>
      <link>https://alexis-catherine.github.io/post/american-alpine-club/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 May 2020 16:52:02 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://alexis-catherine.github.io/post/american-alpine-club/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;My collaborator 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://rachelkeuler.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Rachel Keuler&lt;/a&gt; and I were selected to recieve a grant from the American Alpine Club to investigate the impacts of rock climbing on smooth rock tripe lichen.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Westarctica Finalist</title>
      <link>https://alexis-catherine.github.io/post/westarctica-finalist/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 May 2020 12:13:33 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://alexis-catherine.github.io/post/westarctica-finalist/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Being selected as a finalist for the Westarctica Conservation Scholarship gave me the opportunity to consider how to communicate our work on lichen to a broader audience. Though I wasn&amp;rsquo;t ultimately selected to recieve the Westarctica Conservation Scholarship, I am excited for the new connections and opportunities for collaboration! The 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.westarctica.info/scholarship&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Westarctica Conservation Scholarship&lt;/a&gt; is funded through 2024, so consider applying next year!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Read my grant application below:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In 20 words or less, describe the research question you are addressing.&lt;/strong&gt;
How do microcommunities of cliff-dwelling plants and fungi respond to human-driven disturbance and climate change?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What is the broad problem this question is addressing?&lt;/strong&gt;
Lichens are a symbiotic relationship between an algal and a fungal species. Rock tripe lichen, the focus of my research, is a flat, foliose lichen that can grow up to 60 cm in diameter. Because they are so large, they act as a microhabitat for plants and other species of fungi to grow on. Lichen themselves are known to be an indicator for climate change, particularly their surface growth rates are incredibly sensitive to small changes in temperature and precipitation. Rock tripe lichen tend to occur on cliff faces that are popular with the recreational rock climbing community, meaning that they are not only vulnerable to climate change, but also to anthropogenic disturbance and damage from climbers. Studies have shown that rock tripe lichen themselves can survive low levels of rock climbing damage, but no study has looked at how the microcommunities living on their surfaces are impacted by disturbance or climate change. I will be assessing the sizes of rock tripes on climbed and unclimbed boulder faces in the Shawangunk Mountains of New York State and the community complexities of the microvegetation they support to identify the combined impacts of climate change and anthropogenic disturbance on the rock tripe lichen and the microcommunities on the surfaces. These microcommunities of vegetation provide food for a variety of cliff-dwelling species, including birds, insects, and reptiles. So a reduction in the community complexity or amount of vegetative cover can mean a significant reduction in the nutrition available for species at higher trophic levels, causing a cascade through the ecosystem. Better understanding how this system is impacted by climate change and recreational climbing will help us to manage the recreational access to the sites to preserve both access to the wildlands (a critical part of environmental advocacy) while preserving and protecting the ecosystem from the impacts of climate change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why should the public care about your question/the problem/your research?&lt;/strong&gt;
When we think about climate change, we tend to think about things on a big scale—global super storms, extinction of polar bears, the destruction of redwood forests—but climate change is also impacting microprocesses, nearly unnoticed phenomenon like the cycling of nutrients in the soil, the timing of insect emergence, and the composition of microcommunities on cliff faces. These microprocesses, however, are foundational to understanding the large-scale, global impacts of anthropogenic climate change because large-scale changes are often caused by a network of microchanges. Few research resources are dedicated to understanding the complex web of impacts climate change is having on these ecosystems and organisms. In my research, better understanding how climate change is affecting vegetation microcommunities helps us better predict changes at higher levels in the cliff ecosystem; like impacts on the cascade of animals that depend on these plants and fungi for food, including insects, birds, and mountain lions. Better understanding the wide-reaching impacts of small disturbance helps us better understand what types of actions we can take to mitigate climate change impacts—both large and small.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What possible solutions to climate-change might your work propose?&lt;/strong&gt;
One possible solution revealed by my work to mitigating the impacts of climate change may be to rotate which cliffs are allowed to be climbed during each season. This may be able to mitigate the combination of climate change and climbing impacts (impacts we suspect feed off of each other and are not simply additive). We also expect to find that the growth rates of the rock tripe lichen themselves are very sensitive to climate change (there is a historical dataset for the boulders we are sampling that provides the coverage and size of the rock trip lichen in 1956, 1975 and 2013). Rock tripe lichen are very well distributed throughout North America, and we suspect that they may be very good indicators of the impacts of climate change on cliff and high-altitude communities. If we are able to quantify these results, we hope to use them to compare the impacts of climate change on different high-altitude communities so that we can support localized advocacy against climate change with direct indicators of the severity of impacts facing both human and ecological communities. I also hope that this research underscores the need for investigations into the foundational processes that are disrupted by climate change. Understanding, projecting, and mitigating the effects of climate change require a strong understanding how the network of impacts can cause cascading crises and impacts and I hope my work highlights how we need to be aware of all of these potential problems.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>National Microbiome Data Collective Champion</title>
      <link>https://alexis-catherine.github.io/post/nmdc-champion/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 May 2020 14:46:46 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://alexis-catherine.github.io/post/nmdc-champion/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Founded to support the long-term advancement of microbiome science, the National Microbiome Data Collaborative is building an open-source, agile, integrated data system. Our scientific mission is to provide comprehensive discovery of and access to multidisciplinary microbiome data.
NMDC Champions understand and appreciate the value of well-curated data, and are willing to advocate for the importance of FAIR microbiome data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://microbiomedata.org/nmdc-champions/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Check it out!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>46 Questions</title>
      <link>https://alexis-catherine.github.io/post/46-questions/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 May 2020 17:57:12 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://alexis-catherine.github.io/post/46-questions/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Scientists* are characterized over and over again by the same few stereotypes: that we’re anti-social, disinterested in society, and work-obsessed. But these negative stereotypes are harmful on so many levels. They feed into negative ideas of science and scientists and actually influence how messages are received outside of the scientific community. The narrow presentation of scientists as being only from certain genders, races, backgrounds, and career trajectories also influences who enters STEM fields, and who stays there. We know how important representation and inclusivity are, and we want to broaden the heck out of them in our field.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We here at 46 Questions want to elevate the voices of underrepresented peoples in science-oriented careers and to foster a sense of community in the sciences. We want to showcase the diversity that makes us strong and to make scientists more relatable at the same time, both to the rest of the world and to each other. How? Easy: we hit scientists with 46 rapid-fire questions, they answer, and we share the results. It’s quick, painless, and hopefully fun!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://46questions.wordpress.com/2020/05/11/alexis-garretson/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Check it out&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ESIP Collaboration Areas Update</title>
      <link>https://alexis-catherine.github.io/post/esip-collaboration-areas-update/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Apr 2020 18:02:10 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://alexis-catherine.github.io/post/esip-collaboration-areas-update/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;ESIP is home to 30+ vibrant and diverse community-driven collaboration areas centered around Earth science data challenges and opportunities. Several collaboration areas will share lightning presentations about their recent activities and efforts to increase the use and value of Earth Science data. This webinar aims to broaden awareness of ESIP collaboration area activities, increase communication and collaboration between existing collaboration areas, and invite new participants to join.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://youtu.be/e_hr_XHlX10?t=787&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Check it out!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>GBIF Biodiversity Open Data Ambassador</title>
      <link>https://alexis-catherine.github.io/post/gbif-ambassador/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Apr 2020 23:09:13 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://alexis-catherine.github.io/post/gbif-ambassador/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The success of GBIF depends in part on establishing a good understanding within research and policy communities of the benefits and opportunities provided by free and open access to biodiversity data, as well as the importance of responsible use of such data through proper citation and attribution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The GBIF Secretariat and GBIF participant nodes work to promote this understanding through their communication platforms, at meetings and across networks around of the world. However, this relatively small group can never hope to reach all relevant communities without assistance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Biodiversity Open Data Ambassadors can fill that gap. If you are a biodiversity professional who promotes the principles and best practices of open data sharing and use, we can equip you with information resources, networking opportunities and recognition to make you an even more effective advocate in your own professional communities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;ps://www.gbif.org/article/6dNF1d0tgcI4cmqeoS2sQ4/biodiversity-open-data-ambassadors&#34;&gt;Check it out!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Unique Scientist</title>
      <link>https://alexis-catherine.github.io/post/unique-scientist/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Nov 2019 18:01:31 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://alexis-catherine.github.io/post/unique-scientist/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We are a team of scientists striving to encourage the celebration of diversity in science by highlighting the journeys of #UniqueScientists from all over the world. The #UniqueTeam is fueled with a passion to highlight the diverse faces and stories of scientists that give their heart and soul every day for a better future. Our mission is to embrace diversity and share the #UniqueJourney of any scientist who wishes to share their tale with the world. And, that is exactly what you will find on here: stories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Almost daily, you will find on spotlight a brand-new journey. The story of a unique scientist who has shared a little bit about their lives with the hope to inspire current and future generations to follow their dreams. Our vision is to create an atmosphere that helps others realize that their self-identity should never be a determining factor in the career you choose. #UniqueScientists is more than a group of scientists sharing their stories. #UniqueScientists is a movement and a force that welcomes the journey of every scientist and uses it to empower a brighter future.

&lt;a href=&#34;https://uniquescientists.com/2019/11/30/unique-scientist-alexis-garretson/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Check it out!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mercatus Alumni Spotlight</title>
      <link>https://alexis-catherine.github.io/post/mercatus-alumni-spotlight/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2019 18:01:19 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://alexis-catherine.github.io/post/mercatus-alumni-spotlight/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Mercatus Joseph Schumpeter Fellowship alum Alexis Garretson (GMU ’18) chose to study biology because she likes thinking about complex systems, and was originally drawn to George Mason University because of its partnership with the Smithsonian. Alexis graduated in 2018 with a major in Biology and minors in Public Health, Global Conservation, and Economics. After finishing the first year of her master’s degree at Brigham Young University (BYU), she returned to Mason to complete her MS in Biology, concentrated in Evolutionary Biology.
[Check it out!] (&lt;a href=&#34;https://asp.mercatus.org/essays/alumni-spotlight-alexis-garretson&#34;&gt;https://asp.mercatus.org/essays/alumni-spotlight-alexis-garretson&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ESIP Community Fellows Blog</title>
      <link>https://alexis-catherine.github.io/post/esip-community-fellows-blog/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Sep 2019 18:02:49 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://alexis-catherine.github.io/post/esip-community-fellows-blog/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;ESIP Community Fellow and M.S. student, Alexis Garretson, reflects on her summer fellowship with the Environmental Data Initiative, an ESIP Partner Organization, and how the Data-at-Risk Matrix in development by the ESIP Data Stewardship Committee aided her in this work.

&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.esipfed.org/student-fellow-blog/edi-fellowship-2019&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Check it out!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>EDIs Featured Data Contribution</title>
      <link>https://alexis-catherine.github.io/post/edis-featured-data-contributions/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Jul 2019 18:01:05 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://alexis-catherine.github.io/post/edis-featured-data-contributions/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;EDI successfully completed its second Summer Fellowship Program (10 June – 9 August 2019). We supported nine fellows at host sites located in different parts of the country, studying a large variety of ecosystems, with the host institutions differing in size and data management resources. Each fellow made a significant contribution to publishing the host site’s data for long-term data preservation (securely archived with a unique digital object identifier – doi), making the data discoverable (in the EDI repository, DataONE and by internet searches) as well as to fulfill the requirements of scientific journals and funding agencies such as the National Science Foundation. We also supported the development and publishing of a workflow for marine image analysis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My dataset on amphibian breeding was highlighted as EDI&amp;rsquo;s featured data contribution.

&lt;a href=&#34;https://environmentaldatainitiative.org/edis-featured-data-contributions/mohonk-preserve-amphibian-and-water-quality-monitoring/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Check it out!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SGCI Science Ambassador</title>
      <link>https://alexis-catherine.github.io/post/sgci-science-ambassador/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Feb 2019 18:01:46 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://alexis-catherine.github.io/post/sgci-science-ambassador/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;SGCI has launched a new program to create a network of representatives who would like to share information about gateways on their campuses, in their organizations, and in distributed projects. Gateway Ambassadors serve as community builders, making connections and creating a network between people, experts, and resources.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Gateways Ambassador community will be built with the goal of learning from peers about new technologies and a way to share information and best practices. We&amp;rsquo;ll plan periodic webinars and face-to-face meetings at conferences and have also set up a Gateway Ambassadors Google Group and encourage all involved to contribute to the conversation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://sciencegateways.org/-/congratulations-to-the-2019-sgci-science-ambassadors-&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Check it out!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Arctic Vegetation and Avenues for Herbarium-Driven Research</title>
      <link>https://alexis-catherine.github.io/post/arctic-summer-college-talk/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Jul 2018 18:01:58 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://alexis-catherine.github.io/post/arctic-summer-college-talk/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Herbarium specimens can be used for more than documentation of occurrence and can help support broad investigations into the impacts of climate change on arctic vegetation.

&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ZktcRJvM2d4&amp;amp;feature=youtu.be&amp;amp;t=4704&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Watch my talk here!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
